A Finding Aid to the Colin de Land Collection, 1968-2008, bulk 1980-2003, in the Archives of American Art AAA.delacoli
Archives of American Art
Colin de Land papers
bulk 1980-2003
1968-2008, bulk 1980-2003
AAA.delacoli
Archives of American Art
15.4 Linear feet
The Colin de Land papers measure 15.4 linear feet and date from 1968 to 2008, with the bulk of the collection dating from the early 1980s through 2003. The majority of the collection consists of photographic material, primarily snapshots, documenting daily life in and around de Land’s gallery American Fine Arts, Co., as well as de Land's pesonal life and affairs. There are candid photographs of exhibition openings, day-to-day gallery operations, art fairs, vacations, social gatherings, and New York City street scenes. Also included are some personal objects belonging to de Land and his wife Pat Hearn, as well as two scrapbooks containing items once decorating the walls of de Land’s office at American Fine Arts. The collection includes video material documenting trips to Cape Cod, Hearn’s illness, and occasional art world events.
De Land, Colin, 1955-2003
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged in 4 series:
Series 1: Photographic Material, 1968-2003, bulk 1980-2003 (14 linear feet; Box 1-14)
Series 2: Scrapbooks, circa 1980s-2003 (0.2 linear feet; Box 19)
Series 3: Video and Film Recordings, circa 1980-2003 (0.9 linear feet; Box 15, 16, 18)
Series 4: Artifacts, 1988-2008 (0.3 linear feet; Box 14, 17, 19)
Biographical/Historical note
Colin de Land (1955-2003) was a gallery owner whose New York City spaces challenged traditional modes of exhibition and art dealing.
Raised in Union City, New Jersey, de Land came to the art world from an academic background, having studied philosophy and linguistics at New York University. In 1984, de Land opened Vox Populi, a largely unrenovated space in the East Village, at 511 East 6th Street. The gallery showed experimental work by emerging artists, including the enigmatic John Dogg, thought to be a collaboration between de Land and artist Richard Prince.
In 1986, De Land opened his longest standing gallery, American Fine Arts, Co. (AFA), in the same space previously occupied by Vox Populi. The gallery moved to SoHo in 1988, first to 40 Wooster Street then to 22 Wooster Street in 1993. During the late 1990s, as most SoHo galleries moved to Chelsea, AFA remained a mainstay of the downtown arts scene. De Land’s wife, Pat Hearn, whom he married in 1999 after over a decade together, was also a well known art dealer. Her gallery, Pat Hearn Art Gallery, also moved from the East Village to SoHo, later becoming one of the first to set down roots in Chelsea.
Known for his eccentric fashion and unorthodox business style, de Land cultivated a culture of experimentation within the AFA community. He typically hired young art students or recent graduates, often nurturing their own artistic careers. Along with a group of Cooper Union graduates, many of whom worked at the gallery, he founded the artist collective Art Club 2000. De Land often showed artists working in hybrid media, for example film and photography or music and installation. He was especially interested in ecological and environmental art, as well as work that took as its subject exhibition practice and the act of creating art. He often staged large thematic group shows. Artists who showed at the gallery included Mark Dion, John Waters, Andrea Fraser, Moyra Davey, Dennis Balk, Peter Fend, Tom Burr, James Welling, Mariko Mori, Dan Graham, Jessica Stockholder, Alex Bag, Christian Philipp Muller, and Jack Pierson.
In 1994, de Land and Hearn, along with gallerists Matthew Marks and Paul Morris, established the Gramercy International Contemporary Art Fair. Fashioned after the tradition of inexpensive hotel art fairs, four galleries were invited to exhibit artwork in rooms of the Gramercy Park Hotel, to be sold in a cash and carry model. The fair became an annual event, branching out to other cities, including Miami and Los Angeles, and growing significantly in size in New York. It later became known as The Armory Show.
De Land often carried a point-and-shoot camera and kept several on hand in the gallery. He documented opening receptions, art world social gatherings, concerts, and day-to-day happenings and invited visitors to the gallery and employees to do the same.
After Hearn’s death from liver cancer in 2000, de Land became involved with Kembra Pfahler, the performance artist and leader of the rock band The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black. De Land took over Hearn’s Chelsea gallery, operating it as a second location of AFA. Following his own struggle with cancer, de Land passed away in 2003. AFA remained open, closing at the end of 2004 with a tribute group exhibition to de Land.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. The audio visual material in this collection has access restrictions and requires written permission for use.
Scope and Contents note
The Colin de Land papers measure 15.4 linear feet and date from 1968 to 2008, with the bulk of the collection dating from the early 1980s through 2003. The majority of the collection consists of photographic material, primarily snapshots, documenting daily life in and around de Land’s gallery American Fine Arts, Co., as well as de Land's pesonal life and affairs. There are candid photographs of exhibition openings, day-to-day gallery operations, art fairs, vacations, social gatherings, and New York City street scenes. Also included are some personal objects belonging to de Land and his wife Pat Hearn, as well as two scrapbooks containing items once decorating the walls of de Land’s office at American Fine Arts. The collection includes video material documenting trips to Cape Cod, Hearn’s illness, and occasional art world events.
The bulk of the collection consists of snapshots, along with their negatives and the envelopes provided by commercial photographic printers. The envelopes are sometimes annotated. The photographs, not typically identified by photographer, were taken by de Land, Hearn, and gallery employees, artists, and visitors. Most of the snapshots provide a candid record of life within de Land’s circle, and not formal documentation of gallery exhibitions.
The figures in this collection often occupied blurred boundaries between artist, gallery employee, critic, and friend. Many of the photographs include AFA staff, including Daniel McDonald, Patterson Beckwith, and Craig Wadlin. Also of note are photos showing AFA artists, including John Waters, Mark Dion, Andrea Fraser, Moyra Davey, Dennis Balk, Peter Fend, and Jack Pierson.
In addition to life within the gallery, de Land’s cameras also documented a larger art world of the era, candidly showing openings at other galleries, art fairs such as Art Basel, Art Cologne, and the Berlin Artforum, as well as festivals including the Venice Biennale and Documenta, many of which included AFA artists. There is some documentation of the Gramercy International Contemporary Art Fair and The Armory Show. The photographs frequently include de Land and Hearn’s friends and fellow art dealers Paul Morris, Matthew Marks, and Carol Greene. Some images include artists that showed at Pat Hearn Art Gallery, such as Mary Heilmann. Collectors, celebrity visitors to the gallery, and critics also occasionally appear in the photographs. There is one 1968 photograph of de Land's mother and a small number of 1970s images of both de Land and Hearn.
In addition to the snapshots, there are a variety of other photographic formats in the collection. The contents of the slides are of similar nature to the snapshots. The contact sheet binders offer some formal exhibition installation documentation, but are not exhaustive.
The collection also includes film and video footage. Thirty-five reels of Super-8 motion picture film primarily documents frequent vacations to Cape Cod, as well as the final stages of Hearn’s illness and subsequent death. The 31 DV-mini cassettes include similar content, and some footage of opening receptions and other art world events.
Most of the official gallery records are missing, most likely lost in the frequent floods in the gallery basement. Two scrapbooks include material that was often photographed on the walls surrounding de Land’s desk at AFA. Additional artifacts include one small painting by artist Charles Clough, inscribed to Hearn, a baseball hat frequently worn by de Land and appearing in many of the snapshots, and one page of an autographed calendar.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Colin de Land papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2008 by Dennis Balk, an artist represented by American Fine Arts, Co. and a close friend of de Land.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Audiovisual materials (DV mini-cassettes, Super 8 film, and one audio recording) described in Series 3 have been digitized and are available by special request.
American Fine Arts, Co..; Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.); Art Cologne.; Art Forum Berlin.; Balk, Dennis; Beckwith, Patterson; Biennale di Venezia; Davey, Moyra; Dion, Mark, 1961-; Documenta.; Fend, Peter; Fraser, Andrea; Greene, Carol; Heilmann, Mary, 1940-; International Art Fair; Marks, Matthew; McDonald, Daniel; Morris, Paul; Pierson, Jack, 1960-; Wadlin, Craig; Waters, John, 1946-; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Video recordings
- Photographic Material, bulk 1980-2003; 1968-2003; Series 1; 12 Linear feet Box 1-12
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is Colin de Land’s photographic archive, most of which are snapshots. De Land is frequently cited as never having been without a camera. He invited anyone visiting the gallery or working with him to document daily comings and goings. The resulting images are a candid representation of the gallery’s activities, as well as de Land and his circle’s personal lives. Documentation of AFA exhibitions is limited. Descriptions of the contents of each folder are meant to highlight notable names and events and do not provide a comprehensive description of every photograph - most of which were unidentied except for notations on the envelopes.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged into 3 subseries:
  1.1: Snapshots, 1968-2003, bulk 1980-2003
  1.2: Other Formats, circa 1977-2003
  1.3: Slides, circa 1980-2003
  - Snapshots, bulk 1980-2003; 1968-2003; 1.1
    Although there are some early snapshots depicting Vox Populi and the 1980s New York City art scene, the majority of the snapshots document American Fine Arts, Co. in the 1990s. They candidly depict daily life in and around the gallery, opening receptions, and social gatherings. There are images of AFA staff, artists, and visitors, as well as figures from the larger art world, however most are not identified except for notations on the envelopes. There are also snapshots of the the Gramercy International Contemporary Art Fair and its successor, The Armory Show, vacations in Cape Cod, and trips to international art fairs and festivals such as Documenta, the Venice Biennale, and Art Cologne. De Land was interested in the confluence of art and commerce; many photographs include advertisements, television screens, and other signifiers of consumer culture. Some groups of photographs are identified as belonging to Pat Hearn.
    Snapshots are arranged in rough chronological order, one roll of film per folder, mostly according to the date of event or subject depicted in the image. Dates have been assigned to the closest approximation possible. In some cases, when no information could be drawn from the contents of the roll of film, folders were dated according to the printing stamp on the backs of the photographs.
    Folder headings were derived from de Land’s inscriptions on the envelopes where possible. Where notes did not exist, thematic headings have been assigned by the archivist. The heading "Various Subjects" is used to describe rolls of film that include several events or locations. "American Fine Arts" is used to describe rolls of film with various subjects, but all physically located at AFA. The gallery maintained a numbering system for the photographs, utilizing a combination of numbers and letters. These labels can be found on the commercial printing envelopes, which have been stored in each folder. The meaning of the code has not been identified.
    At the end of the series, there are several folders of unsorted snapshots. These represent clusters or unlabeled envelopes of mosty unrelated photos found together.
    - Mountains, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land and unidentified woman [Magda?] in a small town during the winter.
    - Polaroids, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes Polaroids of Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, [Richard Prince?], [Nils Norman?], artwork by [Basquiat?]. Also includes one Polaroid of Colin de Land inscribed on verso: “Vol 93.6m 1995, 9-9.8 1:58pm Merry Christmas, Edward Braddock” and one Polaroid altered with marker.
    - Pat Hearn Polaroids, Personal, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      Includes Polaroids of Colin de Land and Pat Hearn at home as well as at a party. Also includes Polaroids of artwork.
    - Pat Hearn and Andy Warhol, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes a photograph of Pat Hearn and Andy Warhol signed by Warhol.
    - Baird Jones Photos, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land and Andy Warhol at the Guggenheim Museum; Colin de Land, Mark Kostabi, Jonathon Adolph, and Russel Buckingham at American Fine Arts. Photos by Baird Jones.
    - Beach, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land and [Magda?] on the beach.
    - Prince/Spellman Wedding, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes photos of wedding between Richard Prince and Lisa Spellman, with Pat Hearn and Colin de Land.
    - Deconstructed Taxi, circa 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, [Magda?], [Mark Dion?] with a deconstructed taxi.
    - American Fine Arts, 511 East 6th Street, circa 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes photos of American Fine Arts in its location at 511 East 6th Street, New York. Included are photographs of Colin de Land, Jack Pierson and others installing an exhibition related to a deconstructed taxi, possibly a John Dogg installation.
    - Paravision LA, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land in Los Angeles at the Margo Leavin Gallery, Tropicana Motel, Ankrum Gallery, and La Cage Aux Folles.
    - Madonna Concert, Madison Square Garden, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn and Massimo Audiello.
    - Madonna Concert and Gallery, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn and Massimo Audiello at a Madonna Concert at Madison Square Garden and images of Mary Heilmann and Massimo Audiello in a gallery, possibly the gallery referred to as the “6th Street Gallery below."
    - Colin de Land and Pat Hearn, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes portraits of Colin de Land and Pat Hearn.
    - Colin de Land, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
      Includes portraits of Colin de Land, Patterson Beckwith, Daniel McDonald, Pat Hearn, Chi Chi, and Craig Wadlin.
    - House, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes photos of an unidentified house with art collection.
    - American Fine Arts, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes photos are of American Fine Arts office, with Daniel McDonald and artwork by Art Club 2000.
    - Dancing Woman, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Susa Templin, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land at an exhibition, stamped with Susa Templin contact information on verso.
    - Bowling, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes contact sheets of bowling in Germany, with Pat Hearn and Jutta Koether.
    - Colin de Land Birthday and Various Subjects, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn and a birthday celebration with Aleta Hamada, Dr. Hamada, and Colin de Land’s aunt. Also includes an abstract Polaroid signed on the verso For Colin, For the Fish, [M.S.G?].
    - Natural History Photographs, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes negatives only for rephotographed natural history images.
    - Art Fair, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes a photo of Colin de Land and Patterson Beckwith at an art fair. Includes additional negatives with no prints.
    - Frankfurt, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, Peter Fend and a J. Saint Bernard exhibition, possibly at Ryszard Varisella Galerie.
    - J. Saint Bernard Exhibition, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes installation shots of a J. Saint Bernard exhibition in Frankfurt, possibly at Ryszard Varisella Galerie.
    - American Fine Arts, Germany, Austria, 1990 May (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Includes photos of Mimi Wheeler, Christine Tsvetanov, Margaret Deluccia, Marc Jancou, [Andrea Fraser?], artwork by Jessica Diamond at American Fine Arts. In Europe, photos includes Georg Kargl, [Christian?] Meyer, and artwork by Nicolas Schoffer. Envelope refers also to Kavin Buck, Raymond Pettibon, Helmut Draxler, and Die Aesthetischefeld.
    - Venice, 1990 May (Box 1, Folder 32-35)
      Includes photos taken at the Venice Biennale, with Colin de Land in front a Jeff Koons Made In Heaven sculpture, Peter Fend, Frank Schroder, and Jan Avgikos. Includes additional negatives with no prints.
    - Cady Noland Production, 1990 June (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Includes photographs of the production of neon signs for the Cady Noland exhibition New West—Old West (1990).
    - Cady Noland Exhibition, Santa Monica, 1990 June (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Includes photos of Cady Noland exhibition New West—Old West (1990) at Luhring Augustine Hetzler Gallery, Santa Monica.
    - California, 1990 June (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Includes photos of Shaun Caley Regen, Stuart Regen, Mike Kelley, artwork by Raymond Pettibon, Mike Kelley, and Cady Noland installation for New West—Old West (1990).
    - Peter Fend, Tivat Bay, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Includes photos of Peter Fend’s Tivat Bay during installation with Margaret Deluccia at American Fine Arts.
    - Frankfurt Art Fair, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Includes photos of Peter Fend, Colin de Land, [Noritoshi Hirakawa?]. Photos are inscribed on verso; some photos taken in Paris.
    - Jessica Stockholder Exhibition, Munster, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Includes negatives only for installation shots of Jessica Stockholder exhibition Growing Rock Candy Mountain - Grasses in Canned Sand (1992) at Westfälischer Kunstverein, Münster, Germany.
    - Fend/Japan, circa 1992 January (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes photos of the American Fine Arts booth at an art fair in Japan, with artwork by Peter Fend and Mark Dion. In other booths, artwork includes Pier Paolo Calzolari and Christian Boltanski. Includes photos of Peter Fend and Jeffrey Deitch. This is two combined rolls of film.
    - Japan, circa 1992 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes photos of meal with Peter Fend and others in Japan. Also includes an altered postcard with a woman on the subway and bulldogs.
    - Japan, American Fine Arts, Germany, circa 1992 January-April (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes photos of artwork by Peter Fend and street scenes in Japan; [Benjamin Newman?], Chi Chi, Colin de Land, Margaret Deluccia at American Fine Arts; Georg Kargl and Pat Hearn in Germany.
    - Germany, circa 1992 April (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
      Includes photos taken in Germany of Colin de Land, Esther Friedman, Christian Nagel, [Caroline Nathusius or Lisa Spellman?], Pat Hearn, and Georg Kargl.
    - Art Club 2000, 1993 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes installation shots of an Art Club 2000 exhibition at American Fine Arts, likely Commingle, with Colin de Land and Howard Morse. The envelope includes a note signed Sandra.
    - Christmas, 1993 December (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn and the Rockefeller Center Christmas tree.
    - Peter Fend, Rephotographed Photographs, 1993 December (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - In Front of American Fine Arts, 1993 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of Colin de Land, Daniel McDonald, Ania Corcilius, Ingo Taubhorn, Mark Dion, and Chi Chi.
    - Various Subjects, 1993 December (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn, Colin de Land, Jack Pierson, and Ania Corcilius.
    - Various Subjects, 1993 December-1994 January (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, Ania Corcilius, Mark Dion, Bob Braine, and artwork.
    - Cape Cod, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn, Chi Chi, Dennis Balk, Moyra Davey, Jason Simon, Chandler Hearn, Jack Pierson, and [Marion Hearn?].
    - Providence, Rhode Island, circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn, Chandler Hearn, and Chi Chi.
    - Cape Cod, circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn, Colin de Land, Jack Pierson, Peter Hutchinson, and Chi Chi.
    - American Fine Arts, circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land, Patterson Beckwith, Daniel McDonald, Mark Dion, Francesco Bonami, Robert Storr, Pat Hearn, and Peter Fend.
    - American Fine Arts and New York Street Scenes, 1994 January (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Includes photos of Peter Fend, Daniel McDonald, Ania Corcilius, and Patterson Beckwith.
    - American Fine Arts and New York Street Scenes, 1994 February-March (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Includes photos of Shannon Pultz as artwork by Art Club 2000, [Barbara and Howard Morse?], Christine Tsvetanov, and New York street scenes.
    - First Gramercy, Cape Cod, 1994 April-May (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Includes photos of Colin de Land shaving, Dennis Balk, Chi Chi, Patterson Beckwith, [Josephus Simpson?], Gramercy International Art Fair, Art Club 2000, Untitled (Sears Portrait Center), 1992. Also includes photo of delivery, likely of Vito Acconci artwork Convertible Clam Structure.
    - Cape Cod, Summer 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes photos of Pat Hearn, Mary Heilmann, Colin de Land, Chandler Hearn, Moyra Davey, Jason Simon, David Carrino, Jack Pierson, pie, Chi Chi. Also included in packet, but in a different print format are later photos of Jack Pierson, Recent Work exhibition, Provincetown Art Association, Pat de Groot, John Waters, Carol Greene, [Markus?], Colin de Land, and Kembra Pfahler.
    - Colin de Land, Patterson Beckwith, Daniel McDonald, 1994 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Claudia Schiffer Day, 1994 November 15 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes photos of Claudia Schiffer event at Sam Goody store.
    - Baltimore, 1994 December (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Includes photos of John Waters, Craig Wadlin with artwork by John Waters.
    - Chateau Marmont, 1994 December; 1996 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
      Includes photos of Gramercy International Art Fair at Chateau Marmont in Hollywood, California, with Colin de Land, Pat Hearn, Jack Pierson, Sam Grubman, Lisa Spellman, Matthew Marks, [Nan Goldin?], Craig Wadlin, Paul Morris, Chi Chi, artwork by Art Club 2000 and Mark Morrisroe. Also includes a 1996 photograph of Colin de Land being filmed at American Fine Arts.
    - Various Subjects, 1994 December (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Includes photos of Dan Graham, Patterson Beckwith, Colin de Land, Daniel McDonald, David Karlin, Peter Fend, Barbara Morse, Howard Morse, artwork by Jessica Stockholder, and the Rockefeller Center Christmas tree.
    - Dan Graham, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Includes photographs by Dan Graham and Robert Smithson rephotographed by Colin de Land. Some have been altered with marker.
    - Mapping, Fend, Unger, Misc., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 27)